Okay, but are there any then
mythological stories that happened
near you or before your eyes.
And still it's not entirely clear, you
write something about this in your book, about how
and who supported the future
unrecognized republics.
How Transnistria emerged,
how Abkhazia emerged, you don't
write anything about South Ossetia, but also...
Roughly the same with all that.
Who helped them, who supplied them with weapons?
Well, our... my view, when
I got closer to this and
got to know them and flew there many times...
So, I formed an absolutely
firm view, which before that
the democrats had voiced, but
it was hard to say, I didn't know.
Not just like that, no, but after talking
with them I had an absolutely clear
understanding that when it started, when
perestroika and glasnost
went beyond themselves,
yes, this, I don't know,
what year, in 78-79.
In 89-89?
Yes, yes, in 88, of course.
So, the process began of forming
independent union republics, and their
demands, but especially, of course,
the Baltics played this role.
That is, they spoke first, and I remember
that speech, I don't remember who exactly
was speaking, but it was a representative
of the Baltics in the Supreme Soviet,
or even at the Congress, the one when
some independent deputies had already appeared,
and he said, I speak as a
representative of a sovereign state,
I don't remember, was it Lithuania or Latvia,
when this all began to unravel, suddenly
they remembered this, first
the Baltics, and then everyone started saying,
wait, we are sovereign states, we
joined the Union, we can
leave the Union, right?
And as a counteraction?
And as a counteraction to this, in the Central Committee and
the KGB an idea emerged that we had to stir up
the autonomous republics now, in order
to confront them with a fact,
for example, the Georgians: if you want to leave
the Soviet Union, then from you
Abkhazia will separate, or South Ossetia,
and the same with Transnistria and so
on, it was artificially created,
because I, for example,
for some time, very closely,
because we tried to do something, and
Pavel Grachev and I met together
with Ardzinba first,
that is, the leader of this
separatist movement in Abkhazia, he was
a Moscow guy, he may have been
ethnically, what do you call it,
Abkhaz,
but in general he lived in Moscow most
of his life, even grew up there, whether he
was in Abkhazia at all or not, and his
wife was absolutely, you know,
we spoke the same language, with the same
Moscow accent and generally
pronunciation specifically
Moscow-style, you understand,
he worked for Primakov at that institute,
what's it called, world economy,
as a junior researcher,
well what kind of revolutionary was he, and
certainly no armed fighter
for freedom, and all that is nonsense,
you see, Ardzinba practically
openly admitted that I was sent
here, you sent me here, well not me,
because I was openly, you know,
a democrat and all that, but Pasha Grachev,
who was simply
a Soviet general before that
and a Hero of the Soviet Union from Abkhazia.
Grachev was aware of everything, so this
literally Grachev was in
the know? Of course, of course, yes,
did he tell you this? Yes, and later.
Were you on good terms with him? Hm?
Were you on good terms with him, did he
tell you this?
Well, we were on good terms, because,
you understand, a foreign minister can't
be in bad relations,
whatever he thinks, with the defense minister,
because these are two sides of one
and the same coin, two mechanisms
for implementing policy.
So Grachev supplied him with weapons
without your knowledge? Yes, absolutely, without
my knowledge, I think to a large extent...
Was Yeltsin aware? Yes, he was aware,
of course, to a large extent because
he really thought this was
some kind of our proxy.
Did he think you were aware, or what? Or
just... I think maybe he
knew they were aware too, and
it was hidden from me,
but for them it was clear, I think, and
so especially, of course, on the ground these
former Soviet generals, they were
all Soviet
generals and Soviet officers,
they probably viewed the Abkhaz, this
Ardzinba, this
separatist movement as their own,
they may even have known well
the story of his appointment,
who this Ardzinba was.
So in Georgia, if people there
are watching us now in Georgia,
this story, from the perspective of modern
Georgia, is described
as a Russian occupation,
that is, in fact that's what it was.
But not quite so, this was not a Russian
occupation, these were peacekeeping forces
that we created,
and that were needed there, because there
was open fighting there, and by then
it was Shevardnadze, who was president,
he agreed to this, and the Abkhaz
agreed to this, we had to stop
the bloodshed, and there were Soviet bases, there
was a large Soviet
military base there, as everywhere.
And on its basis these
peacekeeping forces were created, you understand, they were mostly
the same servicemen,
peacekeeping forces.
And then I insisted on this, and we
did it, it was approved in the CSTO, so-
called, that is, the organization
for security
of these new states.
And to give them an international
character, I think there were one or
two companies, sent by someone,
maybe Uzbeks, or someone else,
they were mostly Russian
servicemen, but it was fundamentally
important, why? Because
these were not Russian forces,
and though their flag was Russian,
this flag was also raised,
that CIS one, by agreement.
Obviously Russian
military didn't need this at all?
No, the military did not want this, not all,
some did, they also did not want
this burden, for them all this
is a burden, you know, the military, as a rule,
they do not want war at all, and they do not want
to participate in any conflict
zones, for a simple reason,
because they know people are killed there,
he himself can be killed, and subordinates killed, we
absolutely don't need that. And it was the same
with Russian military, they didn't want
any of this, to participate,
but if they were told they had to
participate and had to
do something there, they did.
When they were told they would perform
peacekeeping functions, that they should not
participate in combat
on either side,
they, by the way, observed this for a long time
and generally almost all the time,
as far as I know, I was there, I traveled there
with inspections and so on,
and until the later events, these ones, and after
those events, after which I stopped
even greeting Ardzinba at all.
What happened with the peacekeepers is that
under the agreement, in order to guarantee
at least that there would be no
use of heavy weapons,
this, by the way, was done in other conflict
zones too, this was a major
negotiating success for us,
that we managed to include this
clause, with which all sides
of the conflict agreed, that is both
the Abkhaz and the Russian peacekeepers,
that to Russian peacekeepers, Russian
peacekeepers would be handed the bolts from guns,
from machine guns and so on,
from everything possible, almost even from
pistols, the bolt that makes a pistol
not a toy, but real,
the bolt, same with a cannon, any one, and
these bolts, especially since the weapons
were Soviet, primitive,
so they all knew perfectly well what
bolts were, and they handed them over, both Georgians and
the others, everyone handed these bolts over
to the Russian peacekeepers,
and that's it, and for some time things
worked like that, and then, of course,
the bloodshed had
a very small scale,
because there, even from a pistol,
especially since all bolts had been collected,
so this
ensured a real ceasefire,
and then negotiations, talks,
that's different, but that's no longer killing and no
destruction, and then in one night the bolts
were handed over only
to the Abkhaz side, while the Georgian bolts
remained under Russian troops' control,
those peacekeepers, and
how and why this happened,
I demanded, you know, explanations,
an investigation, no investigation
was conducted, Yeltsin refused
to authorize an investigation,
and so this question remained, they were not
themselves participants in those events, in the military
actions of Russian troops,
they occupied nothing,
they stood where they had stood, in those
areas designated for
peacekeeping forces, Russian peacekeepers
were located at their
deployment points, the same ones,
but they gave weapons to one side, and
thus the truce was broken, and
of course it was
simply killing after that,
because those were
disarmed, and these Abkhaz were armed.